In this module, we're going to be talking
在本节中，我们将讲解
about variables
变量
and especially what makes variables different
并着重谈论其他语言和 Rust
in Rust as opposed to other programming
在变量上的不同点。
First, we'll cover the syntax to
首先，我们将展示在 Rust 中
declare a variable in Rust.
声明变量的语法。
Then, we'll talk
接着，我们将讲述
about mutability, which is whether
可变性，也就是
a variable is allowed to change its value
是否允许改变一个变量的值。
Finally, we'll discuss how every variable
最后，我们将介绍
in Rust has a type, whether we explicitly
无论是否显式声明类型，Rust 中的每个变量都拥有
annotate that type
确定的类型。
You're probably familiar
你也许已经
with variables from other programming languages.
从其他编程语言的经验中熟悉了变量的概念。
To review, a variable is like a
回顾下，变量就像一个盒子，
cardboard box that you can label
你可以对其命名
and put data into for use later.
并且把数据存进去供之后使用。
Then we write code that operates on the variable
我们写代码时可以通过变量名来操作这个盒子，
name and doesn't need to know what's actually
不需要知道里面到底是什么，
in the box until the program is running.
直到程序运行起来。
Let's talk about how to declare a variable in Rust.
我们来讲讲如何在 Rust 声明一个变量。
All variable
所有的变量
declarations start
在声明时都以
with the let keyword followed
关键字 let 开头，后面跟着
by the name we want. Here,
我们希望的变量名。（译者注，并不是，还有其他的变量声明和使用方式）如图所示，
we're declaring a variable named x.
我们声明了一个名为 x 的变量。
To give variables an initial value,
为了给变量一个初始值，
we use an equals sign
我们使用等号，
and then specify the value we want to
接着写上我们想要赋予这个变量
assign to the variable.
的值。
Here, the value we are choosing is the number 5.
这里，我们选择的值是 5。
Semicolons separate Rust statements.
Rust 语句之间用分号隔开。
Once we have a variable declared, we can
一旦声明了一个变量，
use it by its name.
我们就可以用其名字来使用。
Here's an example
来看这个例子，
with three variables,
有三个变量，
and we've built the value of the variable z
其中 z 是使用
using the values in the variables
x 和 y 的和来初始化的。
A few more things to note about this code:
关于这段代码还有几点要注意：
the main function is a special function
main 函数是特殊的函数，
that's the entry point to binary programs.
它是程序的入口。
It's the function that gets called when we execute
当我们执行 cargo run 时也是 main 函数被调用。
We're going to talk about functions in a future
我们将在未来章节中再讨论什么是函数。
The println! macro  is how you print in Rust.
println! 宏是你在 Rust 中用来打印输出的。
The first argument is the format string
其第一个参数是格式化字符串，
and the curly braces in that format string
格式化字符串里的花括号
are placeholders for the values we want to
是我们想要输出的值的占位符，
print out, which are specified
这些要输出的值在
as the rest of the arguments.
在后面的参数给出了。
The Standard Library documentation has a full
标准库文档给出了
format string reference.
格式化字符串的所有格式参考。
If we switch over to the terminal
当我们切换到终端
and execute cargo run for this program,
并执行 cargo run 来运行这个程序，
we'll see z is 11
可以看到打印出来 z 的值是 11。
Next, let's talk about mutability.
接下来，我们来聊聊可变性。
One thing that's different about variables in Rust
Rust 里的变量有些不同，
is that, by default,
默认情况下，
they can't actually vary.
变量是不可变的。
Here's a program where we've declared a variable
这个例子给出了一个变量，
named x with an initial value of
名为 x，初始值是 5。
Then, we try to add 1 to the value
下一行，尝试对 x 加 1 并
and store the result in x.
赋值给 x 。
The red line beneath the code on line 3
第三行代码的下划线
is the IDE signaling that we have a
是 IDE 给出的提示，告诉我们
compiler error on that line.
这一行有编译错误。
If we build this code in the terminal,
如果在终端中编译这段代码，
we can see the full compiler error,
就能看到完整的编译错误，
which says we cannot assign twice
错误提示说不能为
to the immutable variable, x.
不可变变量 x 两次赋值。
After we assign the value 5 to x,
当 x 被赋初始值 5 后，
we're not allowed to change that value.
就不能再改变这个值了。
The reason Rust variables aren't allowed to change
Rust 变量默认不可变的原因是
by default is to help prevent some bugs.
帮助避免一些 bugs。
Bugs can happen
Bugs 会在这样的情景下发生：
if you look at a value
如果你正在使用某个变量
and assume that value never changes,
并假设它不会改变，
but another part of the program might change
但另一块程序却可能修改了变量
that value and violate your assumptions.
的值并因此打破了你的假设。
Instead, Rust encodes the assumption
与此相反，Rust 用
that a value will never change by making
变量默认不可变
that the default for variables.
来保证上述假设。
To make sure all parts of a program agree
如果要在程序中使得
that a variable is allowed to change,
一个变量是可变的，
we have to explicitly opt in to allowing mutability.
我们必须要显式地声明。
The way to make a
声明一个
variable mutable is
变量的方式
with the mut keyword. By
是使用 mut 关键字。
saying let mut x =﻿,﻿
使用 let mut x = 的形式，
we're then allowed to change the value of x whenever
就可以随时通过对 x 重新赋值，
we want by reassigning to it.
来改变它的值了。
After adding mut to the previous example,
在前一个例子中添加了 mut 之后，
the program compiles without any errors
编译就没有错误了，
and prints the value of x is﻿ 6﻿.
并且打印出了 x 的值是 6。
The last big difference between variables
Rust 中的变量和别的语言相比
in Rust and variables in some other languages
有一个很大的不同点，
is that every variable
那就是每个 Rust 中的变量
in Rust has a type.
都有类型。
These two variables have different types
图中的两个变量基于他们包含的值
based on the values they contain.
而拥有不同的类型。
If we want to annotate the type of a variable,
如果要标注一个变量的类型，
we can by putting a colon after
可以在变量名后放置一个冒号
and then the type after the equals sign.
接着写类型名（在等号前）。
In our previous examples,
在前一个例子中，
we didn't have to say that x was an i32,
并不需要明确指出 x 是 i32 类型。
though. Rust was
Rust 能够
able to figure that out based on the value,
根据赋予的值 5，
5, that we assigned to it.
来推断变量的类型。
If you'd like to annotate your types as you're learning,
如果想要明确标注变量类型，
feel free.
没问题。
However, most idiomatic Rust
然而，更加符合 Rust 风格的写法是
you'll see doesn't annotate types
不标注变量类型，
except for situations in which Rust
除非发生不标注 Rust 编译器
can't figure out the type you want without
就无法推断变量类型的
an annotation.
情况。
If you're ever unsure of the type of something
如果对一个变量的类型不是很确定，
you have, a trick to figure that out
有一个小技巧，
is to annotate the variable
那就是对该变量
with a type that it definitely isn't.
标注一个肯定是错误的类型。
For example, say we have a variable,
例如，
y,﻿ that has the value true
这里有个变量 y，它的值是 true，
and we want to find out the type of the value
而我们想知道 true 的类型是什么。
true. We know that
由于可以确定 true 的类型
it's definitely not an
肯定不是 i32，
We can annotate y as type i32.
所以可以为 y 标注类型 i32。
The compiler error we get tells us
此时的编译错误可以指出
that the type of true is bool.
true 的类型是 bool。
In this module,
在本节中，
we've covered how to declare a variable,
我们讲到了如何声明一个变量，
how to make a variable mutable
如何通过 mut 关键字
with the mut﻿ ﻿keyword,
来声明可变变量，
and how every variable has a type.
还有任何一个变量都拥有类型。
In the next video,
在下一讲，